Today we'll be going over the basics of how to use Sympheny.
So we'll do a very simple project just to illustrate how to use the app.
Sympheny is a really flexible software, but there is a lot of data available.
Here i'm selecting solar panels in the database.
We can see that there's quite a lot of technologies and quite a lot of options just for solar panels.
There we have our annual solar irradiance profile.
So the energy diagram will be updated every time you add something to it.
All of the items on our dashboard are interactive.
You can view values, move things around, filter out components, and download the data table with all of the data.
This is what you will see once you've created a new account.
You have access to an example project.
Let's start with creating our first project.
We give it a name.
This will be a demo on the topic of a data center.
We can Give it a location.
This will help you find your projects when you have many.
Now that we have our project, let's open it up.
For now it's empty.
We have a few options here.
We can edit it, of course.
We can also share it with our colleagues.
We'll start by adding an image to illustrate the project.
Here we go.
Let's add an analysis.
Scenarios can be used to compare different situations.
In this case, we want a first scenario to be about solar power only.
So we'll do a very simple project today just to illustrate how to use the app.
We click into the scenario.
Now we are inside the scenario editor.
We can see a number of steps up here.
First let's change the currency.
Maybe for this project we're using euros.
We need to have a stage.
Stages are meant to represent faces in our project.
These are used mostly for very large-scale projects when we are planning the entire heating system of a district, including network, over decades.
Let's say 20 year.
Starting out, we can set the interest rate and the inflation as zero.
This will help us interpret results.
The next step we need to add a hub.
So a hub is a geographical location.
We can use the search function.
We can change the overlay.
I'll simply draw the outline.
This is just to kind of anchor the project geographically and show the stakeholders what we're talking about.
We can also with add-ons extract information directly from the map.
If we want to have surface and heating system for example of a building or a group of buildings that's possible to get directly from the map.
A hub is a geographical location.
If we draw more of them, we can connect them with networks.
This is necessary when we're modeling, for example, district heating or electrical systems, or you have different buildings that are electrically connected.
A hub can be a single building or, in this case, a group of buildings.
Next step is energy carriers.
We'll add these energy carriers automatically by going directly to supply technology.
and adding some from the database.
Sympheny is a really flexible software, but there is a lot of data available.
Here i'm selecting solar panels in the database.
We can see that there is quite a lot of technologies and quite a lot of options just for solar panels.
I'll take the larger array.
These will be cheaper per kilowatt.
And here we have missing energy carriers.
Do you want to add them?
Yes.
So we're adding solar irradiance and electricity.
So we can see that this already has all of the information we need.
This is the efficiency of this technology.
So this is the sun hitting the panel and the electricity produced overall is 18%, including inverter efficiency, inclination, shading, everything.
We have some technical parameters.
We can set the capacity or the production or other limits for the technology.
In this case, we'll just let Sympheny size and optimize this solar field.
We also have all of the cost parameters already entered.
This comes from our database.
We can edit anything we want to or we can leave it as it is.
We also have the possibility to enter values for embedded emissions.
Okay, so now we have our solar panels.
If we go back to energy carriers, we can see that electricity and solar roof has been automatically entered.
If you want, you can change the color or the name.
For this example, we only have one energy demand.
It will be electricity, so electricity that the facility uses.
This is a bit of an odd one.
It's not a standard building, it's a data center.
And we can see that in our database we have a lot of options, but we do not have data centers.
We can still try out something that maybe sounds close, industry warehouse, and see where this will take us.
Here we have a value per square meter coming out for the norms for this kind of building.
In this case, this is not really correct because it's not the one we want to model.
So from the project, we have a value of 1.2 GWh of electricity per year.
We'll enter that here.
Some information on where this data comes from.
Save and close.
And we see that there is quite a lot of variation based on weekends.
Maybe we're not very happy with this one and we want to change it.
we can actually upload our own.
So upload profile, go to downloads, take this one.
It's been updated to something a bit more realistic.
There is quite a number of options here.
We can smooth out the profile if we enter a number between 1 and 20 here.
So there is a lot you can do with Symfony.
This is a simple Excel file with 8,760 values.
You can grab it.
We can open it on the screen to look at the format.
There we see the format.
So it's a simple Excel file with two columns.
We're also going to add an on-site resource for solar power.
You can see that we have two options.
We can add it from the map, so to simulate virtually any location.
But for this case, since we're in Geneva, we're simply going to select here the ones that are available in our database.
So let's say that it's 10,000 square meter of roof surface available.
And we're only going to simulate one orientation.
Here it's going to be 15 degrees east.
And if we click the View button, there we have our annual solar irradiance profile.
Okay, if you've been paying attention, in every step we have some things that are happening below here and on top on top we have the editor for that step.
And below we have a map that i can hide and also an energy diagram.
So the energy diagram will be updated every time you add something to it.
And here we can see on the left the onsite resource, in the middle the technology, and on the right the electricity demand.
Let's add the grid to finish modeling this problem.
So we'll add grid electricity.
This is electricity that can be purchased at let's say 15 cents per kWh.
We can also give a capacity cost in euro per kilowatt per year.
We have a number of technical parameters.
We can limit this on a per hour basis.
The tariff can also be an hourly profile.
We also have parameters for the environment for emissions.
Let's add here 0.1 kilogram of CO2 per kWh.
Let's do the same for the export.
So this will be surplus PV.
It's also electricity that we can sell.
This is positive value and it means we're going to earn money when we're exporting this electricity.
Before we execute and solve this problem, important to take a look at the energy diagram.
We can see that there is no loose ends and our very, very simple problem looks complete.
So we go to execute, give it a name, select the scenario.
Here are different parameters that can be changed to make the solution more accurate or faster.
You can see that we have choices between different objectives that we can use.
Once we have the results, of an execution that will show up here.
Here's where all the history of the execution will be displayed.
You can also access them from here.
We could download the Excel file of all of the parameters used to simulate the scenario.
We can also download all of the results in the Excel format.
We can view the parameters or we can go on our interactive dashboard.
We can head to all stages and display the Pareto front for this very simple problem.
Both solutions are virtually the same.
Once you select a solution, a station, a hub, you get to the detailed view for this result.
All of the items on our dashboard are interactive.
You can view values, move things around, filter out components and download the data table with all of the data.
This Sankey diagram of energy flows is available for every month of the year.
The energy diagram now contains only the technologies that are part of the optimal solution.
We have the solar field, which is about 1700 kilowatt.
That is about what we expect to have for a field that covers 10,000 square meter.
We have an efficiency of 18%.
We know that on average in Europe we get about 1 kilowatt per square meter of ton power.
We multiply that 18% by 10,000, we get about 1,800.
Let's head back into the project and we are going to create a scenario with a battery.
So copy this scenario, rename it.
This will be PV plus 100 kWh battery.
Now head into the scenario.
All of the parameters we set before have been carried over.
So all we need to do is just to add the battery or add it from the database.
I'll rename it battery 100 kWh, because for this one we will not optimize the capacity, we will specify the capacity 100 kWh.
And if we specify the capacity and that can be installed, then it can still not be installed, but must be installed.
So for this scenario we're not giving any wiggle room, the cost parameters leave it the same.
Now that's done, we can go directly to execution, we see that the battery has been added here on the diagram.
We can execute again.
Okay, execution is done.
View results.
Again, we can check out the Pareto font.
This time we can see that the lifecycle cost has been slightly reduced.
The battery saved us about 30K Euro.
The results look rather similar.
The energy stored in the battery is not huge compared to the GWh that's been consumed by the system.
What we can see is the state of charge of the battery that wasn't there before.
Here we see how the battery is used on a daily basis.
The self-sufficiency has been somewhat increased.